Welcome back to Apush in under 3
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. So, there's this big
misconception through the understanding
of US history that the Great Depression
happens and right afterwards the New
Deal comes along and ends the Great
Depression. To put it bluntly, no, the
New Deal does not end the Great
Depression. The technical end comes with
the mobilization for World War II. I'd
say the New Deal itself is more of
something that reshaped the US
government. So, let's recap here.
Herbert Hoover's president, the
depression starts and poor old lad
Hoover over here doesn't really know
what to do and he's criticized heavily
for it. So, when Franklin Delano
Roosevelt or FDR came along as the
Democratic nominee in the 1932 election,
it's a pretty simple and easy victory
for him. Fairly quickly, FDR will
implement his New Deal plan. And this is
quite complex, but to give it a sentence
definition, FDR's New Deal will use
aggressive government intervention to
stabilize the economy, put people back
to work, and prevent another depression
from happening again. The method that
will be used here is something we like
to call the three Rs: relief, recovery,
and reform. Very quickly, you'll start
seeing programs. Let's go through a few
of them. The Civilian Conservation Corps
employed young men in environmental and
infrastructure projects. There were lots
of public works/infrastructure programs
that built roads, parks, dams, schools,
and public buildings. And separate
programs existed for Native Americans,
Puerto Rico, and African Americans. If
you can't tell, all of these existed so
there would be more jobs for people to
get. But what I want you to notice here
is the big contradiction of what we
established back in Unit VI. remember
when America functioned on a hands-off
approach in letting the economy do its
own thing? Now, with this New Deal, it
will easily be up to this point in
history the biggest government
intervention in its own economy that
America has ever had. And since this New
Deal changed American policy so much,
there was quite a lot of debates on both
sides of Roosevelt. Radicals, unions,
and populist movements such as Huey Long
and Father Charles Coughlin will push
Roosevelt to intervene as much as
possible with government efforts. But on
the other side, conservatives in
Congress and the Supreme Court sought to
limit the New Deal's overall scope. An
example of this is the Supreme Court
case Schechter Poultry Corp. vs. the
United States, which struck down parts
of the National Industrial Recovery Act.
And finally, the last thing about the
New Deal is the institutions it created
that still exist to this day. The
Glass-Steagall Act separated commercial
banking from investment banking, and the
Social Security Act gave old-age
pensions, unemployment insurance, and
aid for the disabled. If you can't tell,
everything about this New Deal will
cause working-class communities to
identify more with the Democratic Party.
On the screen now are AP-style questions
for this topic. Pause now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.